<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Uncategorized &#8211; Anibal Damiao</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/uncategorized/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 10:12:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Hold my (gravitational) beer</title>
		<link>/hold-by-gravitational-beer/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 26 Apr 2025 10:12:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=204</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Human #1: &#8220;Every object have gravity&#8221; Human #2: &#8220;We could shoot a bus-sized thing into a planet but nearly miss on purpose in such way that it&#8217;ll slingshot around in another direction even faster, and if we do that over and over again we&#8217;ll accelerate it. If we send it really fast, it&#8217;ll go to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Human #1: &#8220;Every object have gravity&#8221;</p>



<p>Human #2: &#8220;We could shoot a bus-sized thing into a planet but nearly miss on purpose in such way that it&#8217;ll slingshot around in another direction even faster, and if we do that over and over again we&#8217;ll accelerate it. If we send it really fast, it&#8217;ll go to places that we can&#8217;t even imagine today&#8221;   </p>



<p>Human #3, #4 &#8230;. #990,909,999: Oh, but [insert_negativity_about_something_cool_here_] because [_whatever_unrelated_reason].</p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-twitter wp-block-embed-twitter"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="500" data-dnt="true"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">“Let’s throw a probe out to Jupiter, so Jupiter can throw it into the sun, so the sun can throw it outwards so fast that it can catch up to oumuamua” <br><br>Easily an S-Teir mission <a href="https://t.co/d0ftJo8yDN">pic.twitter.com/d0ftJo8yDN</a></p>&mdash; David Willis (@ThePrimalDino) <a href="https://twitter.com/ThePrimalDino/status/1785102611445628977?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">April 30, 2024</a></blockquote><script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>
</div></figure>



<p>The only thing that amazes me more than tech is humans that spend their pointless lives hating on tech. </p>



<p>It&#8217;s often exhausting to witness the negativity-centric &#8220;thinkers&#8221; powered by social media&#8217;s megaphone.</p>



<p>I love the pioneer spirit of the early internet days when outcasts (many descendent from the ideals of the hippie movement) saw the internet as the new frontier where new worlds could be imagined by their minds. We still see this in niches (eg AI nowadays). I wish that dreaming could become a thing for the masses. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>April 25 1974: 50 years with 30% of freedom</title>
		<link>/april-25-1974-50-years-with-30-of-freedom/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 25 Apr 2024 12:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=150</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Portugal is one of the oldest countries in the world but one of the youngest democracies. Anyone that knows how the country is knows how undemocratic this form democracy is and how unfree this freedom is. That&#8217;s a bold statement that makes much more sense under different perspectives: I will take the liberty of defining [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Portugal is one of the oldest countries in the world but one of the youngest democracies. Anyone that knows how the country is knows how undemocratic this form democracy is and how unfree this freedom is.</p>



<p>That&#8217;s a bold statement that makes much more sense under different perspectives: I will take the liberty of defining democracy by the results achieved instead of the simple defining it ability of everyday people to vote). </p>



<p>There&#8217;s this saying: &#8220;<em><strong>Only freedom is free</strong></em>&#8220;</p>



<p>And under that context:</p>



<p><strong>1) Happy 50th birthday, dear home country</strong></p>



<p>You deserved <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnation_Revolution">the Carnation Revolution</a> that stopped a pointless, retarded and regressive dictatorship. The hope for freedom was everything that many could hold onto.</p>



<p><strong>2) Please stop celebrations that constantly avoid to answer how the promised freedom was stolen</strong></p>



<p>The &#8220;problem&#8221; with democracy is that, it is a never-ending evolution and fight to keept it alive. </p>



<p>You don&#8217;t get the right to it by showing up on April 25 1974. You have to keep pushing for it.</p>



<p>It is easy to argue that Portugal changed a dictator for a duopolist group of interests when politicians turned into an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Illiberal_democracy">Illiberal Democracy</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hybrid_regime">hybrid regime</a> that refused to transition from the dictatorship</p>



<p>Portugal (unlike many other countries) moved forward while being stuck in the past. I visited Estonia in 2001 and saw a country hungry for leaving the Cold War behind, hungry to become part of the Western world. Portugal got rid of a dictatorship but got stuck on the transition: illiberal, non-rational socialism became the norm (even inscribed in the constitution) because it was one side fighting others that were trying to turn the country into a fully-Communist regime. </p>



<p>From that point on, lack of quality politicians sentenced the country into a deep rabbit hole that Portugal couldn&#8217;t get out of.</p>



<p>Simple comparison: GDP growth since 1974</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Portugal: 10x</li>



<li>Ireland: 68x</li>



<li>Estonia: ~25-30x</li>



<li>Slovakia=25-40x</li>
</ul>



<p>None of those countries had an easier start than Portugal. </p>



<p>Ie, Potugal could have today a GDP aligned with northern European countries. Is that 70% that didn&#8217;t happen = 70% of freedom stollen? </p>



<p>If so, why tell me again about some red flowers while ignoring the next 50 years Changing that dynamic is the true revolution that Portugal needs.</p>



<p><br><strong>Symptom 1: The eternal ghost of abstention</strong></p>



<p>If you read the media, you find out that Portugal just had an &#8220;historic&#8221; election with higher turnover. Well, with the exception of the first election after 1974, Portuguese NEVER.. had as much participation as Denmark&#8217;s consistent participation (80-86% turnout).</p>



<p><strong>Symptom 2: 1.2 million votes are dumb</strong></p>



<p>If you read the media and look at the reaction of people and parties after the last election, you will notice how radical the left is in Portugal. 1.2M people (33% of votes) that chose a right-wing party raising important issues in a populist tone were literally called dumb and idiots that shouldn&#8217;t be allowed to vote. That&#8217;s not how democracy works. But that&#8217;s how the pseudo-wanna be intellectuals from the dominant hybrid regime decided to handle the new political voice. </p>



<p>There was no interest in saying &#8220;We hear the people and we will address your concerns&#8221; even if your party did not get to govern&#8221;.</p>



<p>There was no interest in recognizing that Germany actually became Nazi when political divisions blocked it parliament&#8217;s ability to function, and that Portugal entered into the exact same tone by ignoring a important faction holding 33% of a fragmented parliament. </p>



<p>There was no interest in recognizing that freedom, and democracy also means to embrace the inconvenient voices.</p>



<p>Ignoring 33% of the voices now because they are inconvenient will turn into 50%+ on the next time that the voiceless have a chance to have a voice.</p>



<p><strong>Symptom 3: Universal free healthcare is not universal or free</strong></p>



<p>Lying is ugly. And Portuguese politicians have been doing it for long. </p>



<p>In 20 years, private health insurance became the norm and private hospitals are now generating profits to shareholders by filling the gap. </p>



<iframe src="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/public-health-expenditure-share-gdp?country=SWE~FRA~DEU~JPN~GBR~BEL~ESP~NZL~CAN~PRT&#038;tab=chart" loading="lazy" style="width: 100%; height: 600px; border: 0px none;"></iframe>



<p>Meanwhile, people don&#8217;t live as long as they can, despite having the best Mediterranean diet in the world.</p>



<iframe src="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/life-expectancy-vs-health-expenditure?time=earliest..latest&#038;country=PRT~CHE&#038;tab=chart" loading="lazy" style="width: 100%; height: 600px; border: 0px none;"></iframe>



<p></p>



<p>The same deception continues happening on all of the most important sectors of society: education, economy and migration.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The rest is noise</title>
		<link>/the-rest-is-noise/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2024 16:53:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=127</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Appreciate those working hard to get us to a better place. If you have some time&#8230;]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Appreciate those working hard to get us to a better place. If you have some time&#8230;</p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="460" height="220" src="/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Screen-Shot-2024-04-17-at-18.52.06.png" alt="" class="wp-image-128" style="width:671px;height:auto" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Screen-Shot-2024-04-17-at-18.52.06.png 460w, /wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Screen-Shot-2024-04-17-at-18.52.06-300x143.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 460px) 100vw, 460px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The golden age of learning</title>
		<link>/the-age-of-learning/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 30 Mar 2024 19:39:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=40</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I just got reminded of the most amazing detail, while applying to a gig in an area outside of my past experience. It is mind-blowing how much knowledge is available online. At the expense of those with ADHD, the curious mind is living in the most amazing era driven by knowledge today. And that knowledge [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I just got reminded of the most amazing detail, while applying to a gig in an area outside of my past experience. </p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<h3 class="wp-block-heading">It is mind-blowing how much knowledge is available online.</h3>
</blockquote>



<p>At the expense of those with ADHD, the curious mind is living in the most amazing era driven by knowledge today. And that knowledge is basically free!</p>



<p>The way engineering happened in the 80&#8217;s vs how it happened after the PC revolution is just mind-blowing!</p>



<p>No one could ever imagine what a 1000x cheaper computer that you can use at home could become. And no one could imagine, how the internet would, AGAIN, super-charge that revolution even further.</p>



<p></p>



<p>I don&#8217;t think humans appreciate this enough. 95+% of the world&#8217;s GDP is today caused by these two massive waves of innovation.</p>



<p>This wonder is at the core of my passion for Tech.</p>



<p>And that wonder mixes with sorrow. I am sorry that some look at progress negatively. But I am also sorry that some tech &#8220;extremists&#8221; often make others scared about what progress and Tech really is.</p>



<p>By definition, Tech is magical and eyebrow-raising&#8230;</p>



<p>But I wonder if &#8220;Tech Positivity&#8221; can become more mainstream.. So more of us can dream.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Podcasts on Health</title>
		<link>/podcasts-on-health/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Mar 2024 19:23:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=194</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[These are my favorite podcasts to learn about yourself: body, mind and spirit. The 5 Pillars of Health and Performance by Andrew Huberman are simple steps that shake us off from the bad habits caused by modern life. Andrew is single-handedly changing biology and science by making it visible to the curious minds. Not many [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>These are my favorite podcasts to learn about yourself: body, mind and spirit.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>The 5 Pillars of Health and Performance</strong> by Andrew Huberman are simple steps that shake us off from the bad habits caused by modern life. Andrew is single-handedly changing biology and science by making it visible to the curious minds.  Not many podcasts make me rewind often: I religiously watch the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@hubermanlab">entire podcast series</a> and I learn tons every single time. </p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hbNpsmOVGt0">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hbNpsmOVGt0</a></p>



<p><strong>Dr Berg</strong> is a top figure on functional medicine on Youtube (ie, the basic elements behind what causes what). Despite selling supplements, his overview on <strong>Ketogenic diet and Intermittent Fasting</strong> is one of my favorite to understand how to simply improve our diets with ketogenic diet (less sugars and starches) paired with intermittent fasting (sporadic periods without food kicks an healthy state that fights the bad aspects of fat).    </p>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AnyFVWwzgJI">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AnyFVWwzgJI</a></p>



<p></p>



<p>The mind blowing <strong>Metabolic Theory of Cancer</strong> and how food is causing modern diseases and killing too much, too early. <strong>Thomas Seyfried</strong> is driving a different wave of science, opposed (but also complementary) to the thesis that cancers are mostly genetic in origin. This is a favorite of mine because it is so grounded on the basics of cellular biology and I hope that humans don&#8217;t make it common too late. Tons of new science is being pushed, but resistance from the &#8220;old way&#8221; is also a relevant factor.  <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MakS2iRkj1Q">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MakS2iRkj1Q</a></p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Robert Greene</strong> is just an author, not a scientist that distills human&#8217;s meaning and purpose in a very grounded way that brings a classic view in modern times that need it.  <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=50BZQRT1dAg">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=50BZQRT1dAg</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The cost of dying before you should</title>
		<link>/the-cost-of-dying-before-you-should/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2024 15:13:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=154</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I'm curious and I read a lot. I curate / condense it here if I care/have time. Use this to get inspired instead of seeing it as advice. When.. .. are we, as a society handling our most fragile well? For instance, is it even ethical for unemployment consultants to push people into night jobs [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<pre class="wp-block-verse has-text-align-right has-small-font-size"><em>I'm curious and I read a lot. </em><br><em>I curate / condense it here if I care/have time. </em><br><em>Use this to get inspired instead of seeing it as advice.</em></pre>



<p>When..</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Night workers die up to 15 years earlier when they work at night [1] [2]</li>



<li>Poor people (Socio-economic status) die 2 years earlier [3] [4]</li>



<li>People under social isolation are 32% more likely to die earlier (14% when reporting feeling lonely) [5] </li>



<li>Mental health doesn&#8217;t help either [6] [7]</li>
</ul>



<p>.. are we, as a society handling our most fragile well?</p>



<p>For instance, is it even ethical for unemployment consultants to push people into night jobs when that decreases life expectancy by up to 13 years?</p>



<p>Are night to workers getting paid 17% more to match their lost lifespan?</p>



<p></p>



<p>I believe that we &#8211; as a society &#8211; need to get serious and act faster to adjust laws and practices to the most recent and exciting knowledge being produced by science.</p>



<p>We live in a unique age for knowledge, specially with regards to how interesting  science is shared online. </p>



<p>My feeling is that there&#8217;s room to outright improve average mortality rates with what we know today. </p>



<p>I&#8217;m often curious about the very interesting findings around..</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>Mental health</li>



<li>Microbial biology&#8217;s impact on health</li>



<li>The metabolic theories, specially on cancer</li>



<li>Industrial vs regenerative vs sustainable food</li>



<li>Microplastics</li>
</ul>



<p></p>



<pre class="wp-block-code"><code>&lt;iframe src="https://ourworldindata.org/grapher/life-expectancy-vs-health-expenditure?country=~DNK&amp;tab=chart" loading="lazy" style="width: 100%; height: 600px; border: 0px none;"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</code></pre>



<p>The graphic above show Denmark 4 years below the best life expectancies and the the impact seems substantially bigger than the potential still available.</p>



<p>Because our diets and day-to-day lives are so detached of Nature, I personally feel that we should act faster under first principles thinking, since we do not need &#8211; and can&#8217;t afford &#8211; long validation timeframes.</p>



<p>It would be a shame to look back and realize that we missed this amazing opportunity.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>NOTES</strong></p>



<p>[1] Åkerstedt T, Narusyte J, Svedberg P. Night work, mortality, and the link to occupational group and sex. Scand J Work Environ Health. 2020 Sep 1;46(5):508-515. doi: 10.5271/sjweh.3892. Epub 2020 Apr 9. PMID: 32270204; PMCID: PMC7737802. <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28159391/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28159391/</a></p>



<p>[2] Fortune, 2024, Shift work can kill you 15 years sooner, warns Whoop’s chief scientist, while dramatically raising your risk for depression and suicide <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/01/04/shift-workers-sleep-mental-health-depression-suicide-whoop">https://fortune.com/2024/01/04/shift-workers-sleep-mental-health-depression-suicide-whoop</a></p>



<p>[3] Stringhini S, Carmeli C, Jokela M, Avendaño M, Muennig P, Guida F, Ricceri F, d&#8217;Errico A, Barros H, Bochud M, Chadeau-Hyam M, Clavel-Chapelon F, Costa G, Delpierre C, Fraga S, Goldberg M, Giles GG, Krogh V, Kelly-Irving M, Layte R, Lasserre AM, Marmot MG, Preisig M, Shipley MJ, Vollenweider P, Zins M, Kawachi I, Steptoe A, Mackenbach JP, Vineis P, Kivimäki M; LIFEPATH consortium. Socioeconomic status and the 25 × 25 risk factors as determinants of premature mortality: a multicohort study and meta-analysis of 1·7 million men and women. Lancet. 2017 Mar 25;389(10075):1229-1237. doi: 10.1016/S0140-6736(16)32380-7. Epub 2017 Feb 1. Erratum in: Lancet. 2017 Mar 25;389(10075):1194. Erratum in: Lancet. 2017 Mar 25;389(10075):1194. PMID: 28159391; PMCID: PMC5368415. <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28159391/">https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28159391/</a></p>



<p>[4] Ugeskrift fo læger, 2017, <a href="https://ugeskriftet.dk/videnskab/lav-sociookonomisk-status-reducerer-levelaengden-med-ca-ar">https://ugeskriftet.dk/videnskab/lav-sociookonomisk-status-reducerer-levelaengden-med-ca-ar</a></p>



<p>[5] Naito R, McKee M, Leong D, Bangdiwala S, Rangarajan S, Islam S, Yusuf S. Social isolation as a risk factor for all-cause mortality: Systematic review and meta-analysis of cohort studies. PLoS One. 2023 Jan 12;18(1):e0280308. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0280308. PMID: 36634152; PMCID: PMC9836313. <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9836313/">https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC9836313/</a></p>



<p>[6] Time Magazine, Mental Illness May Speed Up the Aging Process, Study Finds <a href="https://time.com/6266565/mental-illness-aging-speed-up/">https://time.com/6266565/mental-illness-aging-speed-up/</a></p>



<p>[7] A comprehensive analysis of mortality-related health metrics associated with mental disorders: a nationwide, register-based cohort study<br>Oleguer Plana-Ripoll, PhD, Prof Carsten Bøcker Pedersen, DrMed, Prof Esben Agerbo, DrMed, Yan Holtz, MSc,Annette Erlangsen, PhD,Vladimir Canudas-Romo, PhD,Prof Per Kragh Andersen, PhD,Fiona J Charlson, PhD,Maria K Christensen, MSc, Holly E Erskine, PhD, Alize J Ferrari, PhD, Kim Moesgaard Iburg, PhD, Natalie Momen, PhD, Prof Preben Bo Mortensen, DrMed, Prof Merete Nordentoft, DrMed, Damian F Santomauro, PhD, James G Scott, PhD, Prof Harvey A Whiteford, PhD, Nanna Weye, MSc, Prof John J McGrath, MD †, Prof Thomas M Laursen, PhD † October 24, 2019 <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(19)32316-5/abstract#section-7c530872-6235-4433-899c-b3f276970189">https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(19)32316-5/abstract#section-7c530872-6235-4433-899c-b3f276970189</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Mortality, Veganism and Human Biology</title>
		<link>/mortality-veganism-and-human-biology/</link>
					<comments>/mortality-veganism-and-human-biology/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 11:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=234</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As far as I am concerned, AI/Robotics/Software and Food are the core issues that&#8217;ll define the future of mankind. It is undeniable that the future of Food will be defined by how we treat our planet and how we treat animals. Animals for Food becomes a complicated topic when Science is clear about human biology [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As far as I am concerned, AI/Robotics/Software and Food are the core issues that&#8217;ll define the future of mankind. <br><br>It is undeniable that the future of Food will be defined by how we treat our planet and how we treat animals.<br><br>Animals for Food becomes a complicated topic when Science is clear about human biology and how plant-only diets are depriving us from key nutrients. <br><br>How can we be more conscientious about animal&#8217;s well being when our own biology and our own advantage as a species seem to rely on killing? Veganism either denies this science or simply ignores this. <br><br>I&#8217;ve seen vegans as a loud voice that is needed but I become against the extremist that often permeates since it makes the issue blind and dumbified. That affects the cause and it affects humankind&#8217;s future. <br><br>I&#8217;m currently exploring this topic further..<br><br>I&#8217;ve come to the conclusion that sustainable farming and stopping industrial farming is 95% of the solution. I worry about big corporations replacing farming with industrial synthetic meat because food security is way more serious than energy security (eg EU and Ukraine) or health security (eg pandemic). <br><br>Mortality is a new perspective that I did not consider before. <br><br>Does veganism even make sense when animals seem be unlikely to be aware of mortality, unlike humans?<br> <br> I wonder if mortality is at the center of the entire issue? <br><br>I wonder if humans will clean this Earthy mess because no one likes to live in a messy house anyway, or if we&#8217;ll go a step further by doing more than the science will tells us to?</p>



<p>It is a complex issue if/when mortality, values towards animals and biology are involved. I hope that humans can find a way of reducing the tribalism to achieve a solution that&#8217;s better for all.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/mortality-veganism-and-human-biology/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Oct 7: wars by ignorance</title>
		<link>/oct-7-wars-by-ignorance/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 08 Oct 2023 20:02:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=137</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What a sad day.. Anyone that believes in progress and science must feel incredibly sad how ignorance won. Many got hurt today and many more will get hurt in the days after. It&#8217;s not about which side is right! I cannot believe that some in the western world were chanting while the slaughter was still [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>What a sad day..</p>



<p>Anyone that believes in progress and science must feel incredibly sad how ignorance won. </p>



<p>Many got hurt today and many more will get hurt in the days after. </p>



<p>It&#8217;s not about which side is right! I cannot believe that some in the western world were chanting while the slaughter was still ongoing. Not only because of today, but also because of tomorrow. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The most beautiful force in the Universe</title>
		<link>/the-most-beautiful-force-in-the-universe/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 15:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=55</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As a software engineer, I always loved the notion that humans invented engineering when they stopped believing in magic: they still wanted to experience that magic but they just found out that creating it is the best way to see something that doesn&#8217;t exist yet.&#160; That&#8217;s why &#8220;every new, advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic&#8221; [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As a software engineer, I always loved the notion that humans invented engineering when they stopped believing in magic: they still wanted to experience that magic but they just found out that creating it is the best way to see something that doesn&#8217;t exist yet.&nbsp;</p>



<p>That&#8217;s why &#8220;every new, advanced technology is indistinguishable from magic&#8221; (as famously put by Arthur C. Clarke in his <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clarke%27s_three_laws">Three Laws</a>). </p>



<p>Think about that for a minute: all new technologies always feel a bit amazing and magic.</p>



<p>I never liked chemistry in school though. But I now suspect that it was not my fault. Here&#8217;s a fun perspective that doesn&#8217;t care about chemical groups, periods or atomic weights; a perspective that is, in my opinion, just amazing:</p>



<p>No one told me that hydrogen and helium were the only elements present in the first moments after the big bang. And no one told me that every other element happens by combining these 2 elements with a lot of energy. A LOT!&nbsp;</p>



<p>It doesn&#8217;t make a lot of sense that iron, lithium, gold, uranium or whatever else comes solely from hydrogen and helium. Super novae, cosmic rays, small stars and large stars are basically factories in an expanding universe where absurds amounts of energy and collisions create and spew elements across the universe. This stuff slowly clumps and forms into planets that we later living in.</p>



<p>Those are called <em>nucleogenic reactions,</em> a fascinating topic because they are the force behind all of this magic.</p>



<p>Carbon, for instance is the 4th element most abundant in the universe and it came from the 2 most abundant ones (Helium, Hidrogen). Plus lots of energy.&nbsp; And because carbon is more abundant than, for instance, zinc, we know that zinc is less abundant in the universe and we know that zinc was formed later. Some elements are so complex so they need more extreme forces to happen. The complex elements are linked to the occurrence of those more extreme forces&nbsp;</p>



<p>90 elements are found in nature. But humans are able to create 22 others by controlling big amounts of energy. A good example is the man-made plutonium that is created from uranium. So we know how the recipe works to make crazy complex stuff.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Now why is chemistry more interesting than just H+H+O = water?</p>



<p>For the same reason that may turn the 2030&#8217;s and 2040&#8217;s into a a defining moment for humankind.&nbsp; This week was an eventful one with multiple news around advancements that show that fusion is getting closer. And with the fusion, come immense energy.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Once we control fusion, we will stop worrying about radiation from nuclear/fission. But fusion is extremely hard and we&#8217;ve only been able to create it by spending more energy than it creates. There&#8217;s a threshold when we can start creating energy without having to expend as much to get the process started, and we&#8217;re not there yet.</p>



<p>So why is anything more exciting than that?&nbsp;Because free energy can create every single element in the periodic table from water and air. Imagine that.</p>



<p>We wouldn&#8217;t need to exploit earth anymore or emit CO2 because we&#8217;d control a process that creates anything that we need (lithium, iron, zinc, gold&#8230;). Anything that we will ever need are built from basic chemical elements that we see in the periodic table. So..</p>



<p>A burger is just water + air + energy</p>



<p>A plane is just water + air + energy</p>



<p>Gold is just water + air + energy</p>



<p>&#8230;</p>



<p>Everything could become incredibly cheap since it&#8217;d be abundant. We&#8217;d stop fighting for water, oil or riches just because they&#8217;d be available and instead focus on pushing our dreams even further.</p>



<p>A world unbound by anything but dreams.. Just like magic.. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-embed-handler wp-block-embed-embed-handler wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Major breakthrough on nuclear fusion energy - BBC News" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0fYiNVRmOA4?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Can paper be sustainable at all?</title>
		<link>/is-paper-sustainable-at-all/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[admin]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 15:12:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=47</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There is a big transition (often away from plastics) into sustainable alternatives. When trees are our best technology for carbon capture, is it really sustainable to cut trees to make paper / wood? Even when those trees were initially planted under a commercial context for that sole purpose? We need to think harder about using [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p id="edbf">There is a big transition (often away from plastics) into sustainable alternatives.</p>



<p id="a0b5">When trees are our best technology for carbon capture, is it really sustainable to cut trees to make paper / wood?</p>



<p id="0576">Even when those trees were initially planted under a commercial context for that sole purpose?</p>



<p id="d2a9">We need to think harder about using wood. For instance, agricultural waste like straw can be turned into paper, using bee wax or other natural ingredients as binding. I see efforts to use paper/wood as an alternative to plastics but I don’t see much effort to move away from using trees.</p>



<p id="c223">Relying more on waste materials and less on forestry would remove pressure from forestry, which is a big issue with climate change that is not getting much attention by governments.</p>



<p id="1c1e">I am a strong believer on radical innovation to flip this equation urgently and in using aggressive government incentives to leave nature alone, even when trees were initially planted for commercial purposes.</p>



<p id="2596">In Denmark, where 62% of land is over-used for agricultural purposes, I would conceptually see an aggressive approach to fix this:</p>



<p id="d369"><strong>Convert ~1/4 of current agricultural land into forestry&nbsp;</strong>by giving incentives to convert and to produce more valuable crops on the remaining land.</p>



<p id="3bb8"><strong>Increase area allocated to commercial forestry&nbsp;</strong>to allow broader tree coverage under a better economic foundation.</p>



<p id="22d2"><strong>Tax heavily the use of wood that doesn’t store carbon</strong>. We need to start looking at burning of wood as equivalent to smoking. It needs to be taxed heavily since it won’t help humans or climate and this taxation should finance the increase in forestry area. For instance, wood used in construction or quality furniture holds carbon longer than burning wood for energy.</p>



<p id="b176"><strong>Forbid the use of wood in power plants</strong>, a big issue in Denmark where heating plants import wood chips from abroad. Burning wood is claimed to be a carbon neutral alternative to fossil fuels (it is) but we can use bio-methane as a replacement to gas instead of having to rely on burning nature. Bio-methane can become “double-positive” if it replaces burning of wood. Nature Energy in Denmark calculated that Denmark could fully replace fossil fuel gas with bio-methane, mostly from cow farms.</p>



<p id="9eb5">I’ve done some quick research about the use of agricultural residue to make paper and it seams that the technology exists, although restricted to some kinds of applications because wood pulp is very good and useful for higher quality paper.</p>



<p id="e880"><strong>We need to start thinking differently: nature must trump efficiency.</strong></p>



<p id="43fe">We burn so much oil/diesel/gas because that’s the most efficient way of storing and generating energy.</p>



<p id="2848">Instead, we need to start focusing on technologies that enable alternatives to become feasible with the help of technology, even if that means producing under less efficient economic terms. Our planet will be better if many industries decide to use agricultural waste instead of wood, bio-methane instead of fossil gas, etc.. Industries that increase X% of their profits by using damaging solutions should pay X^2 taxes.</p>



<p id="c69d">Now we only need governmental courage to fix climate change once and for all. That will unfortunately never happen.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
